Welcome, in the last lecture, we set up a way for us to process the climbable surfaces
欢迎，在上一讲中，我们设置了一个方法，让我们处理可攀登的表面
info.
信息。
And now we have the information of the location and the normal and we are also taking multiple
现在我们有了位置和法线的信息，而且我们还将多个
surfaces into account.
面纳入考虑。
And in this lecture, we will look at how we can actually handle the movement of our climbing.
在这一讲中，我们将研究如何实际处理我们的爬升运动。
More specifically, we need to handle the velocity, the rotation, and snapping movement to the
更具体地说，我们需要处理速度、旋转和与表面的捕捉运动。
surface.
表面。
Alright, let's start coding.
好了，让我们开始编码吧。
So I'm going to first close my project.
所以我将首先关闭我的项目。
The first thing that I want to do, I'm going to go to the header file, then scroll up.
我想做的第一件事是，我将进入头文件，然后向上滚动。
I'm going to go to this new character movement component.
我将转到这个新的角色运动组件。
And inside of it, there are two functions that we need to override.
在它里面，有两个我们需要覆盖的函数。
So press Ctrl + F, I'm going to search get max speed.
所以按Ctrl + F，我将搜索获得最大速度。
So this is the first function that we need to override so that we can change our climb
所以这是我们需要覆盖的第一个函数，这样我们就可以改变我们的爬升
speed.
速度。
So I'm going to copy this function and go back to the header file.
所以我要复制这个函数并回到头文件中。
I'm going to paste the function inside of this overridden functions.
我将把这个函数粘贴到这个重载函数里面。
And there's another function.
还有一个函数。
So here I'm going to search for get max acceleration.
所以在这里我将搜索获取最大加速度。
So I'm going to copy this, then I'm going to paste it in my header file.
所以我要复制这个，然后把它粘贴到我的头文件中。
So these are the two functions that we need to override.
所以这就是我们需要覆盖的两个函数。
I'm going to mark this one override.
我要把这一个标记为覆盖。
Alright, I'm going to create two function definitions.
好的，我将创建两个函数定义。
So place this get max speed under this fixix custom.
所以把这个get max speed放在这个fixix custom下面。
So place it in here.
所以把它放在这里。
Then another function.
然后是另一个函数。
And what we need to do inside of these two functions is simple.
在这两个函数中，我们需要做的事情很简单。
So I'm going to check if it's climbing is true.
所以我将检查它的爬升是否为真。
If that's the case, I'm going to return the max climb speed in here.
如果是这样的话，我将在这里返回最大的爬升速度。
And if it's false, then I'm going to return the super version of this function.
如果是假的，那么我将返回这个函数的超级版本。
So type in super and copy this get max speed paste it in here.
所以输入super，然后复制这个get max speed粘贴到这里。
And for this max climb speed, I'm going to create another member variable for it and
对于这个最大爬升速度，我将为它创建另一个成员变量，并且
I'm going to expose it to blueprint.
我将把它暴露给蓝图。
So scroll down inside of this climb BP variables, I'm going to create a new float.
因此，在这个攀登BP变量里面向下滚动，我将创建一个新的浮点。
So copy this line and paste it in here.
所以复制这一行并把它粘贴到这里。
So it's going to be another flow, I'm going to call this max climb speed and give it a
所以这将是另一个流量，我将把它称为最大爬升速度，并给它一个
default value of 100 units.
默认值为100单位。
Then go back to my CPB file.
然后回到我的CPB文件。
Inside of this is climbing, I'm going to return this max climb speed.
在这里面是爬升，我将返回这个最大爬升速度。
Alright, that's the function body of this one.
好了，这就是这个函数的主体。
Then I'm going to copy these lines and I'm going to paste them in this function.
然后我将复制这些行，并将它们粘贴到这个函数中。
So what we need to do inside of this function is in here, I'm going to return max climb
所以我们需要在这个函数中做的是，在这里，我将返回最大爬升
acceleration.
加速。
And for that, I'm going to create a new member variable.
为此，我将创建一个新的成员变量。
So copy this one and paste it in here and change this speed to acceleration and give
所以复制这个变量并把它粘贴到这里，把速度改为加速度，并给它一个默认值300单位。
it a default value of 300 units and copy this variable.
它的默认值是300单位，然后复制这个变量。
Come back to my CPB file, paste it in here.
回到我的CPB文件，把它粘贴在这里。
And if it's climbing is false, I'm going to return the super version of this function.
如果它的爬升是假的，我将返回这个函数的超级版本。
So paste it in here.
所以把它粘贴在这里。
And that's it.
就这样了。
That's the climb speed done.
这就是爬升速度了。
Alright, I'm going to try to compile first to see if there are any errors.
好了，我先试着编译一下，看看是否有什么错误。
Alright, I have a successful compile and I'm going to scroll down to my fixix climb function.
好的，我的编译成功了，我将向下滚动到我的fixix爬升函数。
That's all for this max climb speed and this acceleration.
这就是这个最大爬升速度和这个加速度的全部内容。
And next one, I like to handle this rotation.
下一个，我喜欢处理这个旋转。
And for that, I'm going to create a new function for it.
为此，我将为它创建一个新的函数。
So go back to my header file, scroll up to this climb core, and I'm going to create another
所以回到我的头文件，向上滚动到这个爬升核心，我将创建另一个
function.
函数。
It needs to return an F clock.
它需要返回一个F时钟。
And I'm going to call it get climb rotation.
我将把它叫做 "获取攀登旋转"。
It's going to have one input parameter.
它将会有一个输入参数。
I'm going to call this one delta time.
我将把这个称为delta时间。
Later, we'll need to use this delta time to help us to interpolate our current quaternion
稍后，我们将需要使用这个delta time来帮助我们把当前的四元数插值到
to the target quaternion.
到目标四元数。
So I'm going to create a function definition and I'm going to place the function under
所以我将创建一个函数定义，并将该函数置于
this process climbable surface info.
这个过程中的可爬升表面信息。
So paste it in here.
所以把它粘贴在这里。
And now we don't need to see these two debug lines.
现在我们不需要看到这两条调试线了。
I'm going to delete them.
我将删除它们。
So instead of this function, first I'm going to create a local variable.
所以，首先我要创建一个本地变量，而不是这个函数。
It's going to be an Fquat.
它将会是一个Fquat。
I'm going to call it currentquat and it's going to equal to our updated component.
我将把它称为currentquat，它将等于我们更新的组件。
Componentquat.
元件quat。
All right, this is the current rotation of our character.
好了，这就是我们的角色的当前旋转。
And next thing I'm going to do an if check.
接下来我将做一个if检查。
So if we have an root motion.
所以，如果我们有一个根动作。
So if we want to use the root motion to drive the movement of our character or the current
所以，如果我们想用根运动来驱动我们的角色的运动，或者当前的
root motion has over written velocity.
根部运动已经超过了速度。
Either way, I'm going to return this currentquat.
无论怎样，我都要返回这个当前的quat。
Once we get past this if check, that means we do want to control the rotation ourselves.
一旦我们通过了这个if检查，这就意味着我们确实想自己控制旋转。
And in this case, I'm going to calculate the target quaternion in here.
在这种情况下，我将在这里计算出目标四元数。
So it's going to be another const Fquat.
所以它将是另一个常数Fquat。
I'm going to call it targetquat and I'm going to make a rotation first.
我将把它称为目标四元数，然后我将首先进行旋转。
So it's going to be a rotation matrix double colon.
所以它将会是一个旋转矩阵的双冒号。
I'm going to use the function makeFromX.
我将使用函数makeFromX。
So I'm going to use a vector to make a rotation so that our character can always face the
所以我要用一个矢量来做一个旋转，这样我们的角色就可以一直面对着
climbable surface.
可攀爬的表面。
And this vector here, this can simply be the current climbable surface normal.
而这个向量，可以简单地作为当前可攀爬表面的法线。
And in case you forget, the surface normal is simply a line pointing straight out from
如果你忘记了，表面法线就是一条从脸部向外直射的线。
the face.
面的直线。
But here we want the opposite.
但这里我们要的是相反的。
We want the vector to point to the climbable surface.
我们想让这个向量指向可爬升表面。
So in here we need to inverse this surface normal.
所以在这里我们需要反转这个表面法线。
All right, now we have a rotator and I'm going to convert this to a quaternion.
好了，现在我们有一个旋转器，我要把它转换成四元数。
So we can simply use the function toquat.
所以我们可以简单地使用函数toquat。
And this is our target rotation.
这就是我们的目标旋转。
All right.
好的。
And the last thing I'm going to do an interpolation so that we won't have any jittering movement.
最后，我要做一个插值，这样我们就不会有任何抖动的运动。
So it's going to be an F math.
所以这将是一个F数学。
And to interpolate quaternion, there is a function is called qinterp2.
为了对四元数进行插值，有一个函数叫做qinterp2。
And here we need to fill in the current.
在这里我们需要填入电流。
Well, this will be our current quaternion and the target will be our target quaternion.
那么，这将是我们当前的四元数，目标将是我们的目标四元数。
And fill in the function input delta time and the interspeed.
并填入函数输入的delta时间和interspeed。
Here I'm going to give it a heart quality value of 5.f.
在这里，我将给它一个心脏质量值为5.f。
I think this is more than enough.
我认为这已经足够了。
And then I simply need to return the result of this F math.
然后我只需要返回这个F数学的结果。
I'm going to delete this one.
我要删除这个。
All right, that's the rotation done.
好了，这就是旋转完成了。
I'm going to copy this function and scroll up to this safe move updated component.
我要复制这个函数，然后向上滚动到这个安全移动更新组件。
I'm going to paste the function in here, then fill in the function input delta time.
我要把这个函数粘贴在这里，然后填入函数的输入delta时间。
So copy this and paste it in here.
所以复制这个并把它粘贴在这里。
All right, that's the rotation done.
好了，这就是旋转完成了。
And the last thing that we need to handle, so we need to snap the movement to climbable
我们需要处理的最后一件事是，我们需要将运动锁定在可攀登的
surfaces.
表面。
For that, I'm going to create a new function.
为此，我将创建一个新的函数。
So go back to my header file.
所以请回到我的头文件中。
It's going to be void.
它将是无效的。
I'm going to call it snap movement to climbable surfaces.
我将把它叫做 "将运动与可攀爬表面相扣"。
And it's going to have the same function input delta time.
它将会有同样的函数输入delta时间。
And I'm going to create a function definition.
我将创建一个函数定义。
Place the function under this get climbing rotation.
把这个函数放在这个获得爬升的旋转下面。
So the first thing I'm going to create a const of vector.
所以我首先要创建一个矢量的常量。
I'm going to call this one component forward.
我将把这个称为一个分量向前。
So this is going to be our components forward vector.
所以这将是我们的分量向前矢量。
And use the function get forward vector.
然后使用函数get forward vector。
All right, next vector that we need to get, it's going to be another const of vector.
好的，下一个我们需要得到的向量，它将是另一个向量的常数。
I'm going to call this one component location.
我将把这个称为一个组件的位置。
And it's going to equal to this updated component.
它将等同于这个更新的组件。
Get component location.
获取分量位置。
And then with these two pieces of information, I'm going to create another const of vector.
然后用这两个信息，我将创建另一个向量的常量。
So this one I'm going to call it projected character to surface.
所以这个我将把它称为投影字符到表面。
So here I'm going to first use the current climbable surface location to subtract the
所以在这里我将首先使用当前可爬升的表面位置来减去
component location.
组件的位置。
So here we can get a vector that's pointing from our character to the surface.
所以在这里我们可以得到一个从我们的角色指向表面的向量。
I'm going to start on a new line here.
我将在这里开始一个新的线条。
Then I'm going to project this vector onto this component forward.
然后我将把这个矢量向前投射到这个组件上。
And now the size of this vector is the exact distance for us to snap our character to the
现在这个向量的大小是我们将角色扣在表面的准确距离。
surface.
表面。
And I'm going to create another const of vector.
我将创建另一个矢量的结构。
I'm going to call this one snap vector.
我将把这个向量称为 "捕捉向量"。
So this vector here, I'm going to first get hold of our current climbable surface normal.
所以这个向量在这里，我将首先掌握我们当前可爬升表面的法线。
And I'm going to inverse this normal.
然后我将反转这个法线。
So this will be the direction.
所以这将是一个方向。
And I'm going to multiply this direction with the length of this vector.
我将把这个方向与这个向量的长度相乘。
So use the function length in here.
所以用这里的函数长度。
And this is the vector that we can use to snap our character to the surface.
这就是我们可以用来把我们的角色固定在表面的向量。
All right, with all of this information ready, I'm going to use the function inside the updated
好了，所有这些信息都准备好了，我将在更新的组件中使用这个函数。
component.
组件。
And the function is called move component.
这个函数叫做移动组件。
In here we need to fill in the delta.
在这里我们需要填入delta。
The delta will be the snap vector, multiply this delta time and multiply our max climb
这个delta将是一个快门矢量，乘以这个delta时间，再乘以我们的最大爬升
speed.
速度。
And the next input parameter that we need to fill in is this new rotation.
下一个我们需要填写的输入参数是这个新的旋转。
And it's an Fquart.
它是一个Fquart。
And we can easily get that by using this updated component again.
我们可以很容易地通过使用这个更新的组件来获得这个参数。
So I'm going to start on the new line.
所以我将在新的一行开始。
And I'm going to copy this and use the function get componentquart.
我将复制这个并使用函数get componentquart。
And the third input parameter is B sweep.
第三个输入参数是B扫频。
I'm going to fill in true.
我要填入true。
So by doing this, we'll be detecting any possible collision along the way.
因此，通过这样做，我们将检测到沿途任何可能的碰撞。
All right, that's pretty much it for this function.
好了，这个函数差不多就这样了。
Then I'm going to call this function.
然后我将调用这个函数。
So copy it and paste it in here.
所以复制它并把它粘贴在这里。
And fill in this delta time.
然后填入这个delta时间。
So copy this and paste it in here.
所以复制这个并粘贴到这里。
All right, that's pretty much all we need to do for the movement.
好了，这就是我们需要做的运动的大部分内容。
I'm going to try to compile again.
我将尝试再次编译。
I have a successful compile.
我有一个成功的编译。
I'm going to launch my editor back.
我将启动我的编辑器回来。
All right, go back to my editor.
好的，回到我的编辑器中去。
I'm going to press play in here.
我将在这里按播放。
Then go to the surface, press F. And now you can see we can move along the surface using
现在你可以看到我们可以用以下方法沿着表面移动
the mass climb speed that we just created.
我们刚刚创建的质量爬升速度。
Note that now we can only move left or right.
注意，现在我们只能向左或向右移动。
We cannot move up or down.
我们不能向上或向下移动。
And that's because there's another thing that we need to take care of.
这是因为还有一件事需要我们去处理。
We should handle the movement input differently.
我们应该以不同的方式处理运动输入。
So the default movement code is only suitable for moving the character on the ground.
所以默认的移动代码只适合于在地面上移动角色。
And if we like to move the character on the surface, we'll need to do a little bit of
如果我们想让角色在地面上移动，我们需要做一点儿
math in there.
数学。
And we'll look at how we can do that in the next lecture.
我们将在下一讲中研究如何做到这一点。
So in this lecture, we've taken care of the velocity rotation and snapping.
所以在这节课中，我们已经处理了速度旋转和捕捉的问题。
Feel free to refer back to the video if you need help.
如果你需要帮助，可以随时回看视频。
And I'll see you in the next lecture.
我们在下一讲中再见。
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐响起]
[音乐播放] [音乐播放]
[MUSIC PLAYING]